A Finding Aid to the Virginia Teague papers relating to the Armory Show, 1913-1962, bulk 1913-1917, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Virginia Teague papers relating to the Armory Show
1913-1962
bulk 1913-1917
Archives of American Art
Teague, Virginia Vanderbilt
AAA.teagvirg
Archival Resource Key
0.2 Linear feet
The papers of New York historian Virginia Teague measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1913-1962, with the bulk of materials from 1913-1917. The papers consist of scattered records and papers compiled by Virginia Teague for the intended purpose of writing a history of the 1913 Armory Show, also known as the International Exhibition of Modern Art, organized by the Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS). Documents include correspondence, business records, and printed material mostly in connection with the Copley Society and AAPS.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to orginal papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Virginia Teague papers relating to the Armory Show were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2010 by Adam and Clover Bergmann, son and daughter of Rudolph Bergmann, Virginia Teague's friend. The papers were found in Bergmann's home after his death in 2009.
Biographical / Historical
Virginia Vanderbilt Teague was a historian in New York, N.Y. and Vermont and was the wife of sculptor and painter R. Lewis Teague. The collection consists of material related to the 1913 Armory Show, also known as the International Exhibition of Modern Art. The exhibition opened at the 69th Street Regiment, in New York City, in February 1913, and traveled to Chicago's Art Institute of Chicago, in March, and Boston's Copley Hall, in April.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the Walt Kuhn, Kuhn family and Armory Show records, which contain records of the Association of American Painters and Sculptors kept by Walt Kuhn, Secretary of AAPS. Correspondence (January 1951) between Teague and Vera Kunn in the Walt Kuhn, Kuhn family papers, and Armory Show records in the Archives of American Art shed some light on Teague's intentions to compile a history of the Armory Show and contact she had with others to gather materials.
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York historian Virginia Teague measure 0.2 linear feet and date from 1913-1962, with the bulk of materials from 1913-1917. The papers consist of scattered records and papers compiled by Virginia Teague for the intended purpose of writing a history of the 1913 Armory Show, also known as the International Exhibition of Modern Art, organized by the Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS). Documents include correspondence, business records, and printed material mostly in connection with the Copley Society and AAPS.
There are a few letters from Elmer MacRae and Vera Kuhn to Virginia Teague recalling the Armory Show. There is one letter from Art Alliance of America Secretary, Elizabeth Grimball, to Henry Fitch Taylor advocating "preparedness" for artists in the event of international hostilities.
Records of the Association of American Painters and Sculptors include meeting minutes, 1913-1915, with agendas, drafts and completed reports of proceedings, checklists of attendees, a hand-written statement by Walt Kuhn, signed by Arthur B. Davies and Elmer McRae, and a mimeograph copy of the AAPS Constitution. Additional correspondence is between Henry Fitch Taylor, George Luks, and James Townsen regarding a review published in American Art News.
Records of the Copley Society are mostly related to the Armory Show. Business records include an exhibition contract and daily sales tallies from the Copley Society, which hosted the Boston venue at Copley Hall. Correspondence is with Walt Kuhn, Arthur B. Davies, John Quinn, Holker Abbott, Edward Warren, L. Flanders, and the law firm of Brandeis, Dunbar & Nutter, and regards a disagreement over sharing revenue generated by the Armory Show exhibition; and letters from General Services Administration and the U.S. Treasury Department regarding customs records for the Armory Show.
Printed material includes catalogs and clippings about the Armory Show.
Art historians -- New York (State) -- New York; Taylor, Henry Fitch, 1853-1925; Davies, Arthur B. (Arthur Bowen), 1862-1928; Copley Society (Boston, Mass.); Association of American Painters and Sculptors (New York, N.Y.); Armory Show (1913: New York, N.Y.)
- Virginia Teague papers relating to the Armory Show, 1913-1962; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  The collection includes a few letters from Elmer MacRae and Vera Kuhn to Virginia Teague recalling the Armory Show. There is one letter from Art Alliance of America Secretary, Elizabeth Grimball, to Henry Fitch Taylor advocating "preparedness" for artists in the event of international hostilities.
  Records of the Association of American Painters and Sculptors include meeting minutes, 1913-1915, with agendas, drafts and completed reports of proceedings, checklists of attendees, a hand-written statement by Walt Kuhn, signed by Arthur B. Davies and Elmer McRae, and a mimeograph copy of the AAPS Constitution. Additional correspondence is between Henry Fitch Taylor, George Luks, and James Townsen regarding a review published in American Art News.
  Records of the Copley Society are mostly related to the Armory Show. Business records include an exhibition contract and daily sales tallies from the Copley Society, which hosted the Boston venue at Copley Hall. Correspondence is with Walt Kuhn, Arthur B. Davies, John Quinn, Holker Abbott, Edward Warren, L. Flanders, and the law firm of Brandeis, Dunbar & Nutter, and regards a disagreement over sharing revenue generated by the Armory Show exhibition; and letters from General Services Administration and the U.S. Treasury Department regarding customs records for the Armory Show.
  Printed material includes catalogs and clippings about the Armory Show.
  - Letters to Virginia Teague, 1951-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Alliance of America Preparedness Document, 1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Association of American Painters and Sculptors - Constitution, circa 1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Association of American Painters and Sculptors - Letters Relating to "Art Society Scandal" Editorial in American Art News, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Association of American Painters and Sculptors - Minutes of Meetings, 1913-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Copley Society - Agreement Received from Walt Kuhn, 1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Copley Society - Correspondence Between Copley Society and Association of American Painters and Sculptors, 1913 February-March; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Copley Society - Correspondence Between Copley Society and Association of American Painters and Sculptors, 1913 April; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Copley Society - Correspondence Between Copley Society and Association of American Painters and Sculptors, 1913 May-June; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Copley Society - Correspondence Between Copley Society and Association of American Painters and Sculptors, 1913 July-December; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Copley Society - Correspondence Between Copley Society and Association of American Painters and Sculptors, 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Copley Society - Daily Sales Tallies, circa 1913; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Copley Society - Transcriptions of Copley Society Documents, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Item, circa 1913-circa 1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Printed Material, 1913-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)